A Guide to the Papers of Jane G. Wilhelm, 1936-2000
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Jane G. Wilhelm 1936-2000
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
12018
This collection consists of ca. 8,000 items(23 Hollinger boxes, 9.5 linear shelf feet.)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These papers were given to the University of Virginia Library by Jane Wilhelm through Donald Wilhelm III, Pleasant Hill, California on June 23, 2001.
Biographical/Historical Information
Jane Gilmer Wilhelm was born on November 29, 1914 in Norton, Wise County, Virginia, to banker Henry G. Gilmer (1881-1961) and Allie Blake Gilmer (1890-1966), school teacher and daughter of an Holston Conference Methodist minister. She graduated from Norton High School as valedictorian in 1931, attended William and Mary from 1931 until she earned her diploma in 1935, and received her Masters from Duke University in 1937. Wilhelm also did graduate work at Yale University, Radcliffe College, and George Washington University. She was married in 1938 to Donald Wilhelm, Jr. (1915- ) and divorced in 1964. They had four children, Donald Wilhelm III (1942- ), Henry Gilmer Wilhelm (1943- ), John Warren Wilhelm (1945- ), and Ellen Jane Wilhelm (1948-1985).
Jane Wilhelm began her career in education at Sullins College, Bristol, Virginia, in 1935-1936, and continued as Director of Student Activities, Georgia State College for Women, Milledgeville, Georgia (1937- 1938), Director of Religious Education, Rock Spring Congregational Church, Arlington, Virginia (1951-1952), Special Lecturer in Philosophy and Religion, Grinnell College, Grinnell, Iowa (1949-1951), teacher and Assistant Principal for Instruction, McLean High School, Fairfax County, Virginia (1954-1964), Director of Community Relations for the new town of Reston, Virginia (1964-1969), Principal of Glaydin School, Leesburg, Virginia (1969-1976), and Professor of English and Philosophy, Northern Virginia Community College (1966-1980). Wilhelm was the first female administrator in the Virginia public schools, during the 1950's.
As the director of community relations for the planned city of Reston, Wilhelm began her work as the primary contact with local voluntary agencies and state and county officials before the first building went up in the developing community. She was charged with the task of securing community facilities, such as schools, day care, a hospital, and churches in the new town, creating an infrastructure for social services in Reston. Wilhelm was also responsible for educating potential buyers about the uniqueness of the community, which was open to all races. She also served as president of the Reston chapter of the American Association of Retired Persons and as a member of the Reston Community Center Board of Directors and Learning in Retirement Institute. In 1999, she won the Best of Reston Award for all of her services to that community.
Wilhelm was also active in the civil rights movement, working with other teachers to integrate Fairfax County Public Schools. Along with eight other teachers, she joined the Fairfax County Black Teachers Association.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of the papers, 1936-2000, ca. 8,000 items (23 Hollinger boxes, 9.5 linear shelf feet) of educator and activist Jane Gilmer Wilhelm (1914-2002), daughter of Henry Groseclose Gilmer (1881-1961) and Allie Washington Blake (1890-1966), of Norton, Virginia.
The papers include correspondence, chiefly from family and friends, postcards, news clippings, notebooks, personal diaries recording both her life and ideas, slides, photographs, audiocassettes and memorabilia. The papers document her teaching career, her concern with social issues in Virginia and nationwide, and the foundation of the planned community, Reston, Virginia.
The bulk of the collection consists of personal correspondence, courses taught by Wilhelm, the development of Reston, Virginia, papers pertaining to the Society for Values in Higher Education, and articles and related materials reflecting her interest in Cuba. A significant portion of the papers describe her family life and her travels to China, Cuba, Greece, and Italy after her retirement. Two unpublished memoirs were written in honor of a deceased daughter and grandson..
Organization
These papers are arranged in three series: Series I: Correspondence (Boxes 1-3); Series II: Subject Files (Boxes 4-13); and Series III: Bound Volumes, Photographs, Memorabilia, and Miscellaneous Papers (Boxes 14-23), including slides, photographs, post cards, and photograph albums.
Contents List
- I: Correspondence
  - Correspondence 1933-2000, n.d., (4 folders) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Donna Alvarado, granddaughter 1988-2001 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Birthday Cards 1987-1995, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Cards 1943-1993, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Christmas Cards and Letters 1976-1992, (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Christmas Cards and Letters 1993-1999, n.d., (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Fairfax County Public Schools 1964-1995 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Ellen Jane Gilmer, grandmother 1939-1944 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Henry G. Gilmer, father 1940-1959 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Grandchildren 1986-1998 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Michael Horwatt 1994-1998 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Invitations 1992-2000, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Eugenia Melton and Vera Gilmer, aunts 1977-1996, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Letters to Newspaper Editors 1993-1995 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Recommendations and Support Letters 1985-1995 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: University of Virginia Special Collections Library 1996 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence and Papers: David Wilhelm, grandson 1986-1996, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Correspondence and Papers: David Wilhelm, III, son 1981-1999 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: re Donald Wilhelm, IV, grandson 1986-1987 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Ellen Wilhelm, daughter 1959-1977 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Henry Wilhelm, son, and including some from his father, Donald Wilhelm, Jr. 1959-2000, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Jane Wilhelm and family letters from Burma 1952-1953 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Jane Wilhelm Christmas Letters and Related Material 1976-1987, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: John Wilhelm, son, including some from his father, Donald Wilhelm, Jr. 1962-1963, 1967-2001, n.d., (2 folders) (Box 3)
- II: Subject Files
  - Aging 1992-1998, n.d. (Box 4)
  - American Association of Retired Persons 1988-1990 (Box 4)
  - The Arts 1990-2000 (Box 4)
  - Astral Forecast, Enneagram, Hexagram, I Ching Numerology for Jane Wilhelm 1974-1998, n.d. (Box 4)
  - "A Biography of Ms. Jane Wilhelm" by students at Terraset Elementary School 1998 (Box 4)
  - Lillian Brown 1988-1990, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Business Cards and Ballot Cards for Vera D. Gilmer 1949, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Dr. Eltse B. Carter 1988 (Box 4)
  - Certificates from Norton High School for Perfect Attendance 1927, 1929 (Box 4)
  - Courses Taught by Jane Wilhelm - "Bible as Living Literature" Grinnell College 1950-1951, (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Courses Taught by Jane Wilhelm - "Christian Education in the Church" George Washington University 1951-1952 (Box 4)
  - Courses Taught by Jane Wilhelm - "Proposed Course in Sociology" McLean High School 1959 (Box 4)
  - Courses Taught by Jane Wilhelm - Instruction for Assistant Principals, McLean High School 1959-1964 (Box 4)
  - Courses Taught by Jane Wilhelm - World Religions, Learning in Retirement Institute and Senior Academy, Reston Community Center 1991-1992 (Box 4)
  - Courses Taught by Jane Wilhelm - "Invitation to Philosophy" Learning in Retirement Institute 1991-2000, (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Courses Taught by Jane Wilhelm - Miscellaneous for the Learning in Retirement Institute 1992-2001 (Box 5)
  - Courses Taught by Jane Wilhelm - "Unions: What Does the Future Hold?" Learning in Retirement Institute 1994 (Box 5)
  - Cuba: Articles 1991-1994, 1997, n.d., (3 folders) (Box 5)
  - Cuba: Articles by Promoting Enduring Peace Trip Members 1993-1994 (Box 5)
  - Cuba: Articles re Cuba Information Project 1994 (Box 5)
  - Cuba: Articles - "The Concept of Human Rights: The History and Meaning of its Politicization," by Joy Gordon, Promoting Enduring Peace Cuba Trip Leader 1997 Apr-May (Box 5)
  - Cuba: Correspondence - Adele K. O'Shaughnessy and George E. Everett, Promoting Enduring Peace Cuba Trip Travelers 1993 (Box 6)
  - Cuba: Cuban Democracy Act of 1992, "Torrecelli Bill" 1992-1993 (Box 6)
  - Cuba: Learning in Retirement Institute, "Contemporary Cuba" Course taught by Jane Wilhelm 1993 (Box 6)
  - Cuba: Miscellaneous 1993-1994 (Box 6)
  - Cuba: Notes by Ruth Emerson on Cuba and one letter 1993-1994 (Box 6)
  - Cuba: Promoting Enduring Peace Cuba Tour - Information and Itineraries 1993 Mar 9-19 (Box 6)
  - Cuba: Promoting Enduring Peace Cuba Tour - "The Struggle Against Racism, the Cuban Experience" 1994 Mar 8-18 (Box 6)
  - Cuba: Tourist Materials 1993 (Box 6)
  - Cuba: Travel Notebook and Other Notes by Jane Wilhelm 1993-1994 (Box 6)
  - Cuba: "Will the Revolution Outlast the Revolutionary?" Talk Given by Jane Wilhelm at the Unitarian Universalist Church, Reston, Virginia 1994 Oct 28 (Box 6)
  - Curriculum Vitae and Biographical Information 1995-2000 (Box 6)
  - Death - Advance Directives, Living Wills, and Euthanasia 1977-1997 (Box 6)
  - Death, Estate, and Wrongful Death Suit of Ellen Wilhelm 1985-1988 (Box 6)
  - Death and Grief 1989-1999, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Death Penalty 2000-2001 (Box 7)
  - Diploma - Duke University, Durham, North Carolina 1937 (Box 7)
  - Dissertation by Linda Cato based on the Life of Jane Wilhelm 1997 (Box 7)
  - Education 1937-2001, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Environment 1936-2000, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Fairfax County, Virginia 1985-1999 (Box 7)
  - Fellowship Square Foundation, Inc. - Lake Ann and Tall Oaks Fellowship Houses 1987 (Box 7)
  - Genealogy - Gilmer Family 1942-1999, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Genealogy - "The Gilmers in America" [1897], (Copy) (Box 7)
  - Genealogy - Kolstad Family 1988 (Box 7)
  - Genealogy - Memoir of Jane Ellen Wilhelm by Jane Wilhelm 1987 (Box 7)
  - Georgia Pacific Corporation and T. Marshall Hahn, Jr. 1989-1990 (Box 7)
  - Glaydin School, Lucketts, Loudoun County, Virginia 1954-1994, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Grinnell College, Grinnell, Iowa 1961-1985 (Box 7)
  - Thomas Jefferson 1986-2000 (Box 7)
  - John F. Kennedy Inaugural Invitation, Reception for Distinguished Ladies 1961 (Box 7)
  - Lady Fairfax Award 2000 (Box 7)
  - Lifestyle, Society, and Health 1988-2001, n.d. (Box 8)
  - McLean High School Alumni and Friends Association 1995-1997 (Box 8)
  - Memoirs, Materials for 1987-2001 (Box 8)
  - Memoirs of an Unidentified Individual n.d. (Box 8)
  - Mental Health and Psychoanalytic Theory 1955-1956 (Box 8)
  - Millennium 1999 (Box 8)
  - News clippings re Henry G. Gilmer and Colgate Darden 1942 (Box 8)
  - News clippings re Norton and Wise County, Virginia 1990, n.d. (Box 8)
  - News clippings and Printed re Tibet and the Dalai Lama 1993 (Box 8)
  - News clippings re Jane Wilhelm 1964-2001 (Box 8)
  - Norton High School Valedictory Address by Jane Wilhelm and Related 1931 May (Box 8)
  - Norton, Virginia Centennial 1994-1997 (Box 8)
  - Obituaries and Friend's Deaths 1970-2001, n.d. (Box 8)
  - Passport and Vaccination Record 1963-1979 (Box 8)
  - Politics 1972-1997 (Box 8)
  - Political and Social Issues 1962-2000, n.d. (Box 8)
  - Quotations ca. 1953 (Box 8)
  - Quotations 1958-1994, n.d. (Box 9)
  - Race and Racism 1977-2000, n.d. (Box 9)
  - Religion 1956-2001, n.d. (Box 9)
  - Report Cards and Transcripts of Jane Wilhelm 1920-1931, 1962-1963 (Box 9)
  - Reston: Articles Relating to Reston's History for "Selling Reston as an Open Community" Reston Museum 1998 Feb 26 (Box 9)
  - Reston: Best of Reston Awards 1994-1998 (Box 9)
  - Reston: Board of Commerce, Transportation System and RIBS (Reston Internal Bus System) 1988-1998 (Box 9)
  - Reston: Correspondence of Robert E. Simon, Jr., the developer of Reston, Virginia 1982-1999, n.d. (Box 9)
  - Reston: Early Reston 1964-1991 (Box 9)
  - Reston: Martin Luther King, Jr. Christian Church 1996-1999 (Box 9)
  - Reston: Miscellaneous Development 1984-2001, n.d. (Box 10)
  - Reston: Reston Community Committee Board of Governors 1985 Oct-Nov (Box 10)
  - Reston: Reston Interfaith 1995-2000 (Box 10)
  - Reston: Reston 2000 Task Force 1988 Apr-Jun (Box 10)
  - Reston: Reverend Embry Rucker 1985-1994 (Box 10)
  - Reston: Senior Academy, Reston Community Center, World Religions Class - Materials and Clippings 1996-1998 (Box 10)
  - Reston: Twentieth Anniversary 1985 Mar-May (Box 10)
  - Reston: Unitarian Universalist Church 1991-2000, n.d., (2 folders) (Box 10)
  - Reston: Unitarian Universalist Church - Sermons 1991-1999 (Box 11)
  - School Psychology 1957-1962, 1981 (Box 11)
  - Sermons 1958-1959, 1996, 2000 (Box 11)
  - Society for Values in Higher Education - Correspondence, Newsletters and Budgets 1986-2000 (Box 11)
  - Society for Values in Higher Education - Assistant Directorship 1989-1990 (Box 11)
  - Society for Values in Higher Education - "History of the 1930's Decade" for Fellows Meeting, Emory University, Atlanta, Georgia 1994 (Box 11)
  - Society for Values in Higher Education - "It is Hard to Say Goodbye" 1990 Aug (Box 11)
  - Society for Values in Higher Education - "Life in Performance: Reflections on Ritual, Religion, and Social Value" by Tom F. Driver 1992 Aug 9 (Box 11)
  - Society for Values in Higher Education - Recollections of the 1930s 1977, 1994 (Box 11)
  - Society for Values in Higher Education - "Socialization: Discontents and Contents" and "It Takes a Long Time to Grow Young" 1997 Aug (Box 11)
  - Society for Values in Higher Education - "Struggling with Religious Tradition: My Spiritual Odyssey 1980 Jul (Box 11)
  - Society for Values in Higher Education - 71st Annual Fellows Meeting, Scripps College 1995 Aug 3-8 (Box 11)
  - Society for Values in Higher Education - 73rd Annual Fellows Meeting, University of Maine, at Farmington 1997 Jul 31-Aug 5 (Box 11)
  - Kathryn H. Stone ca. 1950-1996 (Box 12)
  - Trips - China - Fresh Pond Travel and the U.S.-China People's Friendship Association 1978-1979 (Box 12)
  - Trips - Greece - Saga Holidays, including news clippings concerning Greece 1993-1994 (Box 12)
  - Trips - Italy - Saga Holidays, Information and Itinerary 1994 (Box 12)
  - Trips - Italy and Greece - Travel Journals 1994 (Box 12)
  - Trips - Italy - Tourist Materials and Souvenirs 1994 (Box 12)
  - Twin Oaks Community 1990-1997 (Box 12)
  - Virginia Polytechnic Institute 1961-2000 (Box 12)
  - Virginia Polytechnic Institute Board of Visitors Certificate 1968 (Box 13)
  - Virginia Standards of Learning 1995-1997 (Box 13)
  - The William J. Clinton Presidential Foundation - The Clinton Presidential Library 2000 Aug 25 (Box 13)
  - William and Mary, College of 1934-1993, n.d. (Box 13)
  - Writings by Jane Wilhelm 1956-1999, n.d., (2 folders) (Box 13)
  - Writings - Notes and Quotations n.d. (Box 13)
  - Writings by Jane Wilhelm - "Why Am I a Unitarian?" 1979-1994, n.d. (Box 13)
- III: Bound Volumes, Photographs, Memorabilia, and Miscellaneous Papers
  - Bound Volumes - Autograph Book 1926-1932 (Box 14)
  - Bound Volumes - A Book of Days for the Literary Year with Annotations by Jane Wilhelm 1987 (Box 14)
  - Bound Volumes - Calendars 1962, 1989-1999 (Box 14)
  - Bound Volumes - Calendars 1988, 1994-1997 (Box 14)
  - Bound Volumes - Christmas Cards and Gifts 1995, 1999, n.d. (Box 14)
  - Bound Volumes - Journals 1986, 1999 (Box 14)
  - Bound Volumes - Journal of Trip to China 1978 (Box 14)
  - Bound Volumes - Log Book kept by Visitors to The Four Winds Cabin, on Overlook Drive, Valley View Farms, Rileyville, Virginia, owned by Jane Wilhelm 1979-1999 (Box 14)
  - Bound Volumes - Masters Thesis at Duke University, "Some Aspects of the Ethical and Religious Thought of Thomas Jefferson by Lula Jane Gilmer 1937 (Box 15)
  - Bound Volumes - Meditation Journal 1995 (Box 15)
  - Bound Volumes - Miscellaneous Notebooks 1959, 1995, n.d. (Box 15)
  - Bound Volumes - Photo Albums of Trip to China 1978 Nov-Dec, (2 folders) (Box 15)
  - Bound Volumes - Photo Albums of Trip to China 1978 Nov-Dec, (2 folders) (Box 16)
  - Bound Volumes -Photo Album of Trip to Cuba 1993 Mar (Box 16)
  - Bound Volumes - Religion Notes 1989-1994 (Box 16)
  - Bound Volumes - Scrapbook of Cards and Letters of Congratulations upon the Birth of John Warren Wilhelm 1945 (Box 16)
  - Bound Volumes - Scrapbooks of Trip to China 1978 Nov-Dec, (2 volumes) (Box 17)
  - Bound Volumes - Scrapbooks of Trip to China 1978 Nov-Dec, (2 volumes) (Box 18)
  - Bound Volumes - Telephone and Address Books n.d. (Box 19)
  - Bound Volumes - Telephone Answering Books 1997-1998, n.d., (2 folders) (Box 19)
  - Memorabilia - Pencil Tray made from the seats of Miles Stadium 1964 (Box 19)
  - Memorabilia - Plaque from Virginia Polytechnic Institute to Jane Gilmer Wilhelm for service on their Board of Visitors 1968 (Box 19)
  - Memorabilia - Plaque of Theta Rho Lambda Chapter Service Award to Jane G. Wilhelm 1969 (Box 19)
  - Memorabilia - Political and Slogan Pin Buttons 2001, n.d., (2 small boxes) (Box 19)
  - Memorabilia - Umbrella n.d. (Box 19)
  - Memorabilia - Souvenirs from Trips Abroad ca. 1978-1994 (Box 20)
  - Negatives - Trip to China 1978 (Box 21)
  - Negatives - Trip to Cuba 1993 (Box 21)
  - Negatives - Trip to Greece and Italy 1994 (Box 21)
  - Photographs - Family ca. 1940-1997, n.d. (Box 21)
  - Photographs - Family - Henry G. Gilmer, including group shots ca. 1890-1942, n.d. (Box 21)
  - Photographs - Political Figures 1989, n.d. (Box 21)
  - Photographs - Jane Gilmer Wilhelm 1918-1997 (Box 21)
  - Photographs - Trip to Cuba 1993-1994, (2 folders) (Box 21)
  - Photographs - Trip to Greece 1994 (Box 21)
  - Photographs - Trip to Italy 1994 (Box 21)
  - Postcards - Cuba 1993-1994, (2 folders) (Box 21)
  - Postcards - Greece 1994, (2 folders) (Box 22)
  - Postcards - Italy 1994, (2 folders) (Box 22)
  - Slides - China and Hong Kong 1978-1979, (3 folders) (Box 22)
  - Slides - Cuba 1993-1994 (Box 23)
  - Slides - Italy 1994 (Box 23)
  - Slides - Italy and Greece 1994 (Box 23)
  - Slides - Reston 1967 May (Box 23)
  - Slides - Reston, Virginia; Mark Edwards; and a Glaydin School Presentation, etc. 1976-1981, n.d. (Box 23)